[Music]
hello everyone I am Dr anel makija and
Welcome to our special Vlog in the honor
of World Heart Day celebrated on
September
29th so this video is powered by Mohan
foundation and Triumph also powered by
SBI cards and SBI
foundation so today we will delve into
the importance of heart health and how
we all can take steps to take care of
our heart so heart is a Power House of
our body and it nourishes it supplies
blood to our body and nourishes our body
so it is very essential to keep heart
health good to take care of our heart
and how we can try heart health let's
let us understand this so first let us
understand what a healthy heart really
means
it means keeping cholesterol levels in
check managing our blood pressure so
healthy heart muscle helps us to live
longer it reduces the uh risks of heart
disease and its complications so how can
we build that healthy heart muscle in
our
body do you know lifestyle choices
contribute to heart health yes
absolutely balanced diet e involving
fruits and vegetables in your uh diet
and whole grains avoiding smoking
limiting excessive of alcohol intake
regular exercise and U
also removing all the substance use and
managing stress with the help of yoga
breathing exercise mindfulness all these
are contributing factors to maintain a a
good heart health in today's busy
life okay so let me tell you first what
are the foods good for our heart health
first very normal normal fruits and
vegetables we can take avocados berries
whatever we like lettuce tomatoes these
These are good these are good to have
all the fruits and vegetables are very
good for our heart health second U the
whole grains we should avoid flour we
should flour as in the MAA the whole
flour we should avoid that we can
consume oats we can consume oats floor
The Barley uh we can have jar so we can
have light you know floors not that
heavy multigrain or kind of thing um all
these are good for our heart health we
should very important we must understand
that the oils the ghee or you know the
um refined oil they're not good for
heart health so we must either consume a
very extra virgin olive oil very you
know less uh without cooking it more or
we can have sis oil so all these oils
are good for heart health we should
avoid uh ghee and we should
avoid uh refined oils we can also
consume nuts uh they're very good the
you know sesame seeds flax seeds in fact
flax flax seed oil is also good for
heart health so moving further uh things
we can uh enjoy u in food is uh you know
lowfat milk low fat cheese or no fat
milk they are good we should avoid full
cream we should avoid full cream cheese
or you know heavy cheese for that matter
because at the end of the day they are
only causing the blockages in our heart
so it is really important to avoid all
these so even if we like to consume
buttermilk or yogurt we should always
prefer low fat or no fat at all you know
Green yogurt kind of things so these are
the few things few Foods we must keep in
our mind to uh have a good heart health
and try to limit or avoid alcohol and
smoking because these are the main
factors contributing to the damage of
our heart muscle so now very important
what all exercises we need to do to
maintain our heart
health anything anything which is good
uh if we are diagnosed with heart dis we
need to ask from our doctors immediately
do not rush into cardio please ask your
doctors if we are uh you know okay we
are healthy we can do
yoga whatever our strength is we can do
cardio we can do jumping of Rope Rope
jumping we can do we can do swimming but
it is very important to have a
preventive checkup to see your heart
health before jumping to any exercises
uh and if you're regularly doing our
healthy exercises uh we are you know
good to go but there is this one thing
we need to understand that these days
very frequently we are hearing newses of
heart attack young people dying
especially in gyms so you know sometimes
we
exert exert a lot more than what our
body needs exert and do cardio more than
what are what is the demand of our body
so we need to have
a you know a an exercise or any training
under the guidance of a trainer along
with under the guidance of a doctor
along with we need to have preventive
Health checkups done regularly so thank
you so much for joining uh on this
special episode of World Heart Day
remember our heart requires all the care
we can provide so let's make a
commitment to take care of our heart not
just today but every day stay healthy
and keep that heart
strong